Walter Noble Burns papers, 1908-1964 (bulk 1922-1932)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Walter Noble Burns papers, 1908-1964 (bulk 1922-1932)
AZ 291
Burns, Walter Noble
This collection contains manuscripts, notes, correspondence, photographs, clippings, and related material. Several drafts of the manuscripts for The Saga of Billy the Kid, 1925, Tombstone: An Iliad of the Southwest, 1927, The One Way Ride, 1931 and The Robin Hood of El Dorado: the Saga of Joaquin Murrieta, 1932, are present. Correspondents, including Wyatt Earp and various others, relate their experiences.
3.3 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Walter N. Burns was a journalist and author of Western fiction
Organization
This collection is organized into four series:
Series I: Manuscripts, 1922-1964
Series II: Correspondence, 1925-1956
Series III: Short Stories, Articles and Miscellaneous Material, 1922-1927
Series IV: Contributions to the Chicago Newspaper, The Inter Ocean, 1908-1913
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains manuscripts, notes, correspondence, photographs, clippings, and related material. Several drafts of the manuscripts for The Saga of Billy the Kid, 1925, Tombstone: An Iliad of the Southwest, 1927, The One Way Ride, 1931 and The Robin Hood of El Dorado: the Saga of Joaquin Murrieta, 1932, are present. Photographs are of people and places such as Pat Garrett, John Slaughter, Lincoln County, N.M., and Tombstone, Ariz. Correspondents, including Wyatt Earp and various others, relate their experiences. Also included are short stories and articles; many about Wild Bill Hickock. Clippings from his newspaper columns in Chicago's Inter Ocean, 1908-1913, chiefly concern western themes.
Burns, Walter Noble -- Archives; Earp, Wyatt, 1848-1929 -- Correspondence; Murrieta, Joaquín, d. 1853 -- Fiction; Slaughter, John H. (John Horton), 1841-1922; Garrett, Pat F. (Pat Floyd), 1850-1908; Hickock, Wild Bill, 1837-1876; Billy, the Kid -- Fiction; Frontier and pioneer life -- West (U.S.); Outlaws -- New Mexico -- Lincoln County; Outlaws -- Arizona -- Tombstone; Western stories; Tombstone (Ariz.) -- History -- Sources; Lincoln County (N.M.) -- History -- Sources; Correspondence; Manuscripts; Photographs
Container List
- Series I: Manuscripts, 1922-1964
  - The Saga of Billy the Kid, Doubleday, Page & Co., New York, 1925
    - Correspondence: Various. 1922-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence: W. A. Carrell. 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - First Draft. (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    - Second Draft. (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
    - Notes, photographs, miscellaneous material. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Scrapbook of News Clippings. (Box 2)
  - Tombstone; An Iliad of the Southwest, Doubleday, Page & Co., New York, 1927
    - Correspondence. 1926-1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence: Wyatt Earp. 1926-1927 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - First Draft. (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
    - Second Draft. (Box 3, Folder 7-9)
    - Typescript copies of newspaper articles from 1881. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Notes, photographs, clippings. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The One Way Ride: The Red Trail of Chicago Gangland from Prohibition to Jake Lingle, Doubleday, Doran & Co., New York, 1931
    - First Draft. (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
    - Second Draft. (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    - Third Draft (parts). (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Revisions: Chapter 1. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Revisions: Chapters 2-3, 8-9, 12, 16 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Revisions: Chapter 13 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Revisions: Chapter 17 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, clippings. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Notes on revisions, Title Page, Contents. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Nine notebooks. (Box 5)
  - The Robin Hood of El Dorado: The Saga of Joaquin Murrieta, Famous Outlaw of California's Age of Gold, Coward-McCann, Inc., New York, 1932
    - First Draft. (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
    - Second Draft. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence. 1931-1936 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Twelve notebooks. (Box 6)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1925-1956
  - Correspondence: Doubleday, Page & Co., H. E. Maule. 1925-1956 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: General. 1926-1932 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Series III: Short Stories, Articles and Miscellaneous Material, 1922-1927
  - Wild Bill Hickock: Published Articles by Walter N. Burns. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Wild Bill Hickock: Various notes and manuscripts. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Wild Bill Hickock: Correspondence. 1923-1927 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Wild Bill Hickock: Photographs, miscellaneous material. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Articles: Various published and unpublished, and related material. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Article: "If Napoleon had Commanded the Allies." 1922 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Short Stories, published and unpublished. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - California notes. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous items. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    Includes an account of the "Bisbee Massacre" of December 1883, and an essay written by 15-year-old Walter N. Burns on "Mineralogy and Geology" awarded a prize by the Polytechnic Society of Kentucky in 1881.
- Series IV: Contributions to the Chicago Newspaper, The Inter Ocean, 1908-1913
  - "Books and Men Who Make Them," Walter N. Burns' literary column. October 17, 1908-December 11, 1909 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Feature Story: "Railroad Official Writes Novels." November 7, 1909 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Feature Story: "Billy Sunday: A Man's Christian." March 20, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Feature Story: "Genius Behind Prison Walls." April 24, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Feature Story: "Chicago's Religious Awakening." October 30, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Feature Story: "Parole Law Has Increased Crime in Chicago 50 Per Cent." November 13, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Feature Story: "Is Life Imprisonment Worse Than Hanging?" November 27, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Feature Story: "War on Dishonest Gambling Devices." January 1, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Feature Story: "How Condemned Men Die." January 15, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Feature Story: "On the Trail of Frijoles." March 26, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Feature Story: "The Murderous Black Hand." (Crime in Chicago). September 17, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Feature Story: "Adventures of an Unofficial Flirt." September 17, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Feature Story: "Greater Zoo for Lincoln Park." November 19, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Feature Story: "Where the Illinois made Their Last Stand." December 31, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Feature Story: "Chicago's War on White Plague." January 19, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 2)